<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-14T22:49:21+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kalle Moen</title><subtitle>Personal website</subtitle><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><entry><title type="html">How to fail well</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-20-how-to-fail-well/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to fail well" /><published>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-fail-well</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-20-how-to-fail-well/">&lt;p&gt;In my first job, my boss passed down an insight I’ll never forget:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No one cares if you fail, they just care about your rate of improvement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your rate of improvement is acceptable, why should they care? Everyone fails, and given enough time you’ll eventually be where they want you to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems arise when people can’t trust you to improve. That’s what breaks opportunities and relationships, not failing itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, this is the difference between someone failing poorly and someone failing well.
Here are four traps I’ve found that erode that trust:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoiding responsibility
If you don’t think you have a problem, you can’t fix it. Simple as that. Without personal responsibility, there is no improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poor root cause analysis
If you don’t find the root cause of your failures, they will come back and haunt you. There’s little patience for people who repeat the same mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of follow-through
Once you know the problem, you can’t let go of it until you have a permanent system that guarantees it won’t happen again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not capping your downside
You want to be taking big swings, but not so big they take you out of the game entirely. If the downside of failing is too big, you might not have a chance to learn and try again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you avoid these mistakes for a while, next time you fail people around you will shrug their shoulders thinking “Oh well, I’m sure he’s got this”.
And hey, as a bonus you’ll improve faster.
Happy failing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="ideas" /><summary type="html">In my first job, my boss passed down an insight I’ll never forget:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remove steps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-13-remove-steps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remove steps" /><published>2020-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/remove-steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-13-remove-steps/">&lt;p&gt;If you want someone to take a particular action, remove as many steps needed to take that action as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When booking a meeting, instead of saying “When are you available?”, say “I’m available between 1–3pm, let me know a time between those intervals that work for you and I’ll send you a calendar invite.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By front-loading the work you remove friction. Not only are you showing respect for their time, but you’re also increasing your chance of the meeting happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What actions do you want your boss, friends, or clients to take? Are you adding friction you could easily mitigate?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="design" /><summary type="html">If you want someone to take a particular action, remove as many steps needed to take that action as you can.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sub-surface problems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-11-sub-surface-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sub-surface problems" /><published>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sub-surface-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-11-sub-surface-problems/">&lt;p&gt;Tech entrepreneurs often inhabit a very narrow demographic, and they often scratch their own itch or solve problems they see around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of that, there are a disproportionate amount or productivity and dating apps out there. These problems that a majority of entrepreneurs have I call “surface problems”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With good timing and a novel approach, there is a lot of money to be made, but you’ll have to deal with a ton of competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative to solving surface problems is to solve… you guessed it… “sub-surface problems”.
These are problems you can’t know about without being an insider in a specific scene or industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often they require insider knowledge, which heightens the bar for entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you aren’t a magician you won’t know what magicians need or how much money magicians spend on magic tricks and fancy playing cards. The answer is A LOT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving these problems come with a bunch of advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less sexy or more fringe often means less competition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Approaching an industry with beginner’s eyes can give you a leg-up. What looks obvious to you might be foreign to everyone else.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re lucky, the scene or industry can go mainstream, giving you a huge advantage over the incoming competition. A great example of this is computers. Back in the day, they were the interests of scientists and hobbyists. Today they power our entire economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of building another me-to app, flirt with fringe ideas and interests. Eventually, you’ll bump into product ideas with highly motivated markets ready to take your money.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="ideas" /><summary type="html">Tech entrepreneurs often inhabit a very narrow demographic, and they often scratch their own itch or solve problems they see around them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Riding waves together</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-05-riding-waves-together/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Riding waves together" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/riding-waves-together</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-05-riding-waves-together/">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever done a project on your own, you know that motivation follows an oscillating pattern.
Some days are glorious, others are shit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your situation, the valleys can get so deep you eventually throw in the towel. Here’s how that typically looks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/riding-waves-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something peculiar happens when you are two people vested in a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely does the lines of the motivational valleys line up, they’re often out of sync.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your morale is low, your partner’s morale is high and vice versa. You pull each other up when it’s needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/riding-waves-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like real waves, they cancel each other out, and you’re left with a calmer sea. One which doesn’t rip your boat apart before you reach your destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all models, this doesn’t perfectly represent reality, but one thing is clear –if you want to go far, go together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="business" /><summary type="html">If you’ve ever done a project on your own, you know that motivation follows an oscillating pattern. Some days are glorious, others are shit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intent and relationships</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-04-intent-and-relationships/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intent and relationships" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/intent-and-relationships</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-04-intent-and-relationships/">&lt;p&gt;While reflecting on the past year, I realized I had spent a lot of time with people I didn’t enjoy spending time with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sucked for both parties, and it stole time I could have invested in people that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became very clear to me why this had happened after making three lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first list, I wrote down all the people that played a role in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second list, I grouped the same people in three tiers, based on how much they mattered to me.
On the third list, I grouped them based on how often I spend time with them. Weekly, monthly, or quarterly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into it thinking that I must be spending the most time with people that matter most, but the reality was that it was completely random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when I realized that my entire life, I’ve left my relationships up to chance. Spending time with whoever happens to be around at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I’m doing something different. At the start of every week, I look at the list of people that matter the most and ask myself “What can I do this week to strengthen these relationships?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people around us are the most important part of our lives, without them nothing else matters. Why leave them up to chance?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="relationships" /><summary type="html">While reflecting on the past year, I realized I had spent a lot of time with people I didn’t enjoy spending time with.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Judging on single traits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-04-judging-on-single-traits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Judging on single traits" /><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/judging-on-single-traits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020-02-04-judging-on-single-traits/">&lt;p&gt;There are exceptions to this, but very rarely do others judge you based on single traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t hear a lot of people say “That girl has a weird haircut, so I don’t like her as a person.” or “That guy has a weird laugh, so I don’t want to hang out with him”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People look at you as an entire package. Personality, appearance, social circle, the whole shebang.
This might be obvious, but why is to so common to judge ourselves based on single traits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Keep in mind that I’m not talking about people who judge others on traits like race or gender, that‘s a separate issue. I’m simply talking about how others see you on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="relationships" /><category term="ideas" /><summary type="html">There are exceptions to this, but very rarely do others judge you based on single traits.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Magic of Having Nothing to Lose</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019-02-19-nothing-to-lose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Magic of Having Nothing to Lose" /><published>2019-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nothing-to-lose</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019-02-19-nothing-to-lose/">&lt;p&gt;Are you ready to give up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to quit your job, or drop that side project which isn’t going anywhere? Great, then I have good news for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About two years ago I was in your exact position. The company I work for went through a round of lay-offs and I was moved to a role I wasn’t happy in. Ready to jump ship, I was pondering my next move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that time I happened to attend a book signing with Eric Ries at the famous Strand Book Store. Ries was there to promote his new book, The Start-up Way, which was aimed at using entrepreneurial principles inside big organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Q&amp;amp;A, a member of the audience asked Ries how to convince his stubborn boss to let him test ideas inside his company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric response was something to the effect of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If he has different values, it might be easiest to get a new job. But if you’re willing to quit anyway, you might as well tell him he’s wrong. If you get fired you’ll at least stand up for something you believe in, which will attract companies that have similar values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking. If I’m willing to quit, I can try anything to improve my situation without being afraid of losing my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This felt weirdly liberating and got me thinking of ways I could improve my situation that I wouldn’t have entertained before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months, I voiced my opinions more firmly. I told management what I thought could be done better. I pushed for more interesting projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, my situation got better. I was given more autonomy and interesting projects.
Anywhere in life where you’re willing to cut your losses, it opens doors of opportunities that previously didn’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mathsy-angle&quot;&gt;The mathsy angle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to look at it is as an investment with an expected value calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the lay-offs, my job was worth say, 100 units of value. Which meant I had 100 units to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an option came along that could increase the value of my job by 30 units, with a 60% chance of succeeding, but 40% chance of getting me fired, it wouldn’t make sense to pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a random outcome and enough trails, the gain would never make up for the value I would lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calculation before the lay-offs:
(30 * 0.6) + ((-100) * 0.4) = -22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, after the lay-offs, the value of my job had dropped to nearly zero. Suddenly the same option would gain me 30 units, without any downside. In other words, I had everything to gain and nothing to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same calculation after the lay-offs:
(30 * 0.6) + (0 * 0.4) = 30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound obvious, but it’s easy to forget that options can become more lucrative when variables change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re currently thinking of quitting, ask yourself “Are there options I haven’t considered now that the cost of losing is lower?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be leaving options on the table.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kalle Moen</name></author><category term="business" /><category term="ideas" /><summary type="html">Are you ready to give up?</summary></entry></feed>